Finding Aid for Tau Beta Pi, Gamma Chapter (University of Michigan) records, 1906-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Tau Beta Pi, Gamma Chapter (University of Michigan) records, 1906-2008
Tau Beta Pi. Gamma Chapter (University of Michigan)
87368 Bimu F41 2
University of Michigan chapter (established 1906) of the national engineering honorary fraternity; organizational records, including minutes of meetings, correspondence, accounting ledgers, national convention material, newsletters, and yearbooks documenting chapter activities and projects.
8 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated by the fraternity (donor no. 6752 ).
Periodic additions to the collection are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Tau Beta Pi is a national engineering honorary fraternity. It was founded in 1885 by Edward H. Williams, Jr., head of Lehigh University's mining department. Because Phi Beta Kappa, the sole honor society at that time, focused on inducting members studying the liberal arts and sciences, Williams wanted to create a parallel organization that would give recognition for outstanding scholarship in the technical fields. In addition to conceiving of this society, Williams formulated its constitution, governing structure, membership requirements, badge, and certificate, and gave it the name it still holds today. In spring 1885, he invited the class valedictorian, Irving Andrew Heikes, to become Tau Beta Pi's first student member, an offer that was accepted. This parent chapter at Lehigh, Alpha of Pennsylvania, was joined in 1892 by the Alpha of Michigan chapter established at Michigan State Agricultural College (later Michigan State University). National headquarters have been located on the University of Tennessee's campus in Knoxville since 1907. In 1974, Sigma Tau, another engineering honor society, was incorporated into Tau Beta Pi in the belief that a single honor society would best serve the interests of the engineering profession.[1] As of 2012, there were 238 active chapters and over 500,000 members.[2]
In 1906, the Michigan Gamma chapter of this fraternity was established at the University of Michigan, making it the eleventh Tau Beta Pi chapter.[3] Professor R. C. Matthews, General Secretary of Tau Beta Pi, had wanted to see a chapter established at the University of Michigan as chapters had already been founded at Michigan Agricultural College and Michigan School of Mines. One of the main difficulties in establishing the chapter was the fact that the University of Michigan did not have a comparative grading system at the time, instead using a pass/fail model. Thus, there was no way to identify students in the higher grade bracket, one of the membership requirements. After discussion between officers of Tau Beta Pi and faculty representatives of the University of Michigan Engineering Department, the latter agreed to provide small, select lists of upperclassmen who could qualify for membership in Tau Beta Pi. The first initiation ceremony of the new chapter took place June 14, 1906, with 22 members being inducted, including twelve members of the class of 1907, four alumni, and six honorary members. Horace P. Ramey served as first president of the Gamma chapter. In October 1967, Michigan Gamma hosted the 62nd national convention. Women were first granted eligibility for membership in 1969, when five women were initiated into the chapter. Michigan Gamma was awarded the R.C. Matthews Outstanding Chapter Award for the 1977-78 and 1979-80 academic years. In 2006, the chapter celebrated its 100th anniversary.[4]
-----------------------
Notes:
1. One Hundredth Anniversary booklet, 2006, Box 1
2. "Tau Beta Pi General Facts." The Tau Beta Pi Association. http://www.tbp.org/pages/About/GeneralFacts.cfm (retrieved 30 May, 2012).
3. "Michigan Gamma founded 1906." Tau Beta Pi, Michigan Gamma. http://spider.eecs.umich.edu/~tbp/100years/history.php (retrieved 30 May 2012).
4. One Hundredth Anniversary booklet, 2006, Box 1
The records of the chapter have been arranged into nine series: History and By-laws; Record Books; Administrative; Financial Records; Membership - Michigan Gamma; National Tau Beta Pi; Newsletters; Visual Material; and Yearbooks.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Honorary societies.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.
- History and By-laws
  The History and By-laws series includes records relating to the history of Tau Beta Pi, such as Edwin Stackhouse's Beginnings of Tau Beta Pi, as well as the Tau Beta Pi constitution and by-laws. Also contained in this series is material relating to the 100th anniversary of the chapter, most notably a booklet signed by Nobel laureate in physics Samuel C.C. Ting, a member of the chapter from his time at the university.
  - Histories (Box 1)
  - By Laws, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - One Hundredth Anniversary 2006 (Box 1)
    (Includes booklet signed by alumnus Samuel C.C. Ting, Nobel laureate in physics, and letter from Governor Jennifer Granholm)
- Record Books
  The Record Books series contains bound volumes with meeting minutes and membership lists.
  - 1906-1931 (Box 1)
  - 1932-1943 (Box 1)
  - 1944-1956 (Box 1)
  - 1957-1961 (Box 1)
- Administrative
  The Administrative series includes a variety of material relating to the governance of the chapter. Most prominent are correspondence and minutes.
  - Advisory Board 1933-1998 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, meeting notes, and minutes
    - 1912-1922 (Box 1)
    - 1948-1952 (Box 1)
    - 1954 (Box 1)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 1)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 1)
    - 1965 (Box 1)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 1)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 1)
    - 1967, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 2)
    - 1968/1969, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - 1969/1970, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - 1970/1971, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 2)
    - 1977/1978/1979 (Box 2)
    - 1982-1985 (Box 2)
    - Big Ten Council Meeting October 1968 (Box 2)
    - Chapter Surveys 1961-1974 (Box 2)
    - Eightieth Anniversary Banquet 1986 (Box 2)
    - Pledge Instruction Booklets (Box 2)
    - Songbooks (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan-Dearborn campus (Box 2)
  - Initiation Banquet Speeches 1961-1967 (Box 3)
  - Ohio State Run Action Committee 2005 (Box 3)
  - President's Reports 1953-1962 (Box 3)
  - Report of Election of Officers
    - 1906-1962 (Box 3)
    - 1963-2001 (Box 3)
- Financial Records
  The Financial Records series contains mostly accounting ledgers from 1925 until 1977.
  - Accounting ledgers
    - 1925/1926-1930/1931 (Box 3)
    - 1930/1931-1934/1935 (Box 3)
    - 1935/1936-1938/1939 (Box 3)
    - 1939/1940-1945 (Box 3)
    - 1967-1977 (Box 3)
  - Loan Fund (Box 3)
- Membership-Michigan Gamma
  The Membership - Michigan Gamma series includes catalogues of members belonging to the national organization as well as lists and short biographies of Michigan Gamma chapter members.
  - Alumni Biography Project and Responses (Box 3)
  - Alumni History Book 1981 (Box 3)
    (Michigan Gamma 75th Anniversary)
  - Catalogues
    - 1911 (Box 3)
    - 1916 (Box 3)
    - 1932 (Box 3)
    - 1939 (Box 3)
  - List of Michigan members of Tau Beta Pi, Triangles Society, and the Vulcan Society up to 1945 (Box 3)
  - List of Presidents, Advisors, and Distinguished Members 1986 (Box 3)
- National Tau Beta Pi
  The National Tau Beta Pi series contains records from Tau Beta Pi national conventions. Of particular note is the 1967 convention, which was co-hosted by the Michigan Gamma chapter and held in Ann Arbor and Detroit.
  - Conventions
    - 1961 (Box 3)
    - 1962 (Box 3)
    - 1966 (Box 3)
    - 1967 (Box 4)
      (held in Ann Arbor and Detroit)
      - Convention Committee on Rituals (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - General (Box 4)
      - Ladies' Program Committee (Box 4)
      - Photographs (Box 4)
    - 1971 (Box 4)
    - 1976 (Box 4)
    - 1978 (Box 4)
    - 1979 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Council Slate 1961 for 1962-1966 (Box 4)
- Newsletters
  The Newsletters series includes copies of the chapter newsletter The Society Page, with issues from 1978 through 1982.
  - The Society Page, 1978-1982 (Box 4)
- Visual Material
  The Visual Material series contains photographs and slides from various Tau Beta Pi events.
  - Photographs
    - Bent Polishing 1999 (Box 4)
      (includes negatives)
    - Career Fair 1997 (Box 4)
    - Districts/Nationals 1998 (Box 4)
    - Initiation 1998 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous, circa late 1990s (Box 4)
    - Service Projects, circa 1999 (Box 4)
  - Slides
    - Fall 2000 Slideshow, 1980-1999 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous 1977-1999 (Box 4)
- Yearbooks
  The Yearbooks series contains Chapter Surveys, which document the chapter's activities and projects during an academic year. They also include photographs of the events.
  - Chapter Surveys
    - 1973-1974 (Box 4)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 4)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 4)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 5)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 5)
    - 1983-1984 (Box 5)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 5)
    - 1985-1986, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1986-1987 (Box 5)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 6)
    - 1988-1989 (Box 6)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 6)
    - 1990-1991, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - 1991-1992, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - 1992-1993, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - 1993-1994, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - 1994-1995, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - 1995-1996, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - 1998-1999 (Box 7)
    - 1999-2000, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - 2000-2001 (Box 7)
    - 2001-2002 (Box 7)
    - 2002-2003, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - 2003-2004, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - 2004-2005, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - 2005-2006, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - 2006-2007, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - 2007-2008, 3 folders (Box 8)